# Serge Durand

Software Engineer and Backend Lead

linkedin.com/in/sergedurand205----https://github.com/Sergecodes

#### SUMMARY

Pragmatic and experienced software engineer who is well-versed in technology and writing code to create reliable and user-friendly systems that solve interesting problems. I'm also a skilled leader who has proven the ability to mentor and manage a team of professionals to build software.

#### EXPERIENCE

Backend Lead 02/2024 - Present

PKFokam Research Center - Afriland First Bank

- · Lead backend development team in the development of a Core Banking System
- · Work with design patterns such as Api gateway, aggregator, saga/event sourcing, transactional outbox, CQRS
- · Work with technologies such as Expressjs, Nestjs, Springboot, Axon, RabbitMQ, GraphQL, websockets, node-red
- Implement feature flagging on customers with Unleash
- Mentoring and coaching of junior developers and in technical interviewing of new recruits

Software Engineer 03/2023 - 02/2024

PKFokam Research Center - Afriland First Bank

- Worked on microservice and multi-module based applications using Java/Springboot and related technologies
- Implemented backend for Afriland First Bank(AFB) South Sudan's E-Banking web application https://ebanking.afrilandfirstbankss.com
- Implemented back office for AFB Ivory Coast's mobile banking application SARA https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.icafbmobilebanking
- Implemented backend for partner microfinance institutions' mobile applications

**Frontend Developer** 01/2023 - 03/2023

HOUSE INNOVATION SARL

- · Implemented designs and wireframes into frontend interfaces
- · Re-architectured multi-page web apps to single page apps using React and Nextjs
- Used tools like Context api, React query, axios and redux-toolkit to consume backend api and handle state management

#### Software Development Team Lead

04/2022 - 09/2022

University of Yaounde 1 7

- Led a team of 4 developers in the development of a platform for the University of Yaoundé 1 to follow-up thesis process of postgraduate students, using the MERN stack.
- Implemented a robust API for front and backend communication and raised throughput of important requests by over 30% by using a Priority Queue to prioritize incoming server requests.
- Reduced completion date by 2 weeks by applying Agile methodologies and properly tracking issues, using Jira.

**Software Developer** 01/2021 - 03/2022

TechniqConsulting

• Worked in a software development agency where I took part in developing tailored software according to clients' business requirements.

- Tested software for bugs and operating performance by applying unit, integration and stress testing, added documentation, and fixed bugs to increase correctness by over 20%.
- · Suggested using the appropriate technologies and tools per project which in turn increased time to market.

**Django Developer** 06/2021 - 10/2021

CS Portal ↗

• Developed a platform that offers many services to users such as a marketplace, Q/A section and discussion section, among others.

- Used Amazon S3 to host static and media files, and deployed project on the cloud via Azure App Service.
- Scored 97% Performance, 94% Accessibility and 92% Best Practices on PageSpeed Insights.

#### EDUCATION

Computer Science 2022

University of Yaoundé 1 - Bachelor's degree

• I led a team that developed a platform for my university to follow up the thesis of postgraduate students.

### CERTIFICATES

**Enslish Speaking - Expert (Emmersion)** 

12/2022 - Present

DevOps Essentials (IBM)

11/2022 - Present

#### SKILLS

Java/Springboot SQL/NoSQL

Python/Django Team Leadership
JavaScript/TypeScript Software Testing

Reactjs/Nextjs Docker

Node/Express/Nestjs System Design

## LANGUAGES

English Native French Fluent